Finding Aid for St. Andrew's Memorial Episcopal Church, Detroit, Mich., Records 1886-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Andrew's Memorial Episcopal Church, Detroit, Mich., Records 1886-1988, 1944-1969
St. Andrew's Memorial Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
3 oversize volumes
3 linear feet
Historical and other background information; vestry records include correspondence, meeting minutes, reports, registers of church services, and other subject files; records of church organizations; files pertaining to church camp and special church services; printed materials, and photographs.
9477 Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan (donor no. 1059 ) and came to the library in 1993.
The record group is open for research.
St. Andrew's Memorial Episcopal Church grew from very humble beginnings. Started as an Episcopalian Sunday School, the first meeting was held in the front room of a cottage on Merrick Avenue on April 5, 1885. An evening prayer service was held the following month under the direction of Reverend Rufus W. Clark. Services were led by lay readers when it was not possible to obtain the services of a clergyman.
By January 1886, a building had been finished on the corner of Fourth and Putnam The opening service, held on January 17th, was led by Bishop Samuel S. Harris and Ex-Governor Henry P. Baldwin was a guest speaker. In May of that year, Reverend A.A.W. Hastings was installed as permanent rector and served until 1891.
The congregation of the church had begun to grow over the years and it was necessary to have a new building. Designed by neo-gothic architect Ralph Adams Cram, the new church was completed in 1902, and was designated as a memorial to Bishop Harris who had been a patron of the church since its inception. The services in this new building were well attended and the church became known for its Good Friday services.
In 1906, disaster struck on Tuesday during Holy Week. A fire, probably caused by faulty wiring, destroyed the church. During the three years it took to rebuild the church, services were held in the West Side Club on Fourth and Putnam. There was a significant decline in the congregation after the fire and it was several years before the numbers were restored.
During the 1950s, many changes in the surrounding neighborhood affected the church. Houses were torn down, the freeway was built, and Wayne State University expanded. The congregation of St. Andrew's migrated to the suburbs and membership declined from 147 pledging families in 1949 to 87 families in 1961. The 1960s saw great changes for the church. The congregation was still shifting with many old members leaving and new members coming in. In 1962, Wayne State University made an agreement with St. Andrew's whereby the school would lease the sanctuary for use as a chapel for the next 99 years. This was done as a part of the university's student religious center project.
In the 1990s, St. Andrew's played a dual role, serving both the university and the surrounding neighborhoods. St. Andrew's has always been community minded and has offered programs for the community outside of church services. Most recent of these is the "Sunday's at St. Andrew's", a concert series designed to highlight local artists.
The records of St. Andrew's Memorial Episcopal Church (1886-1987) contain items such as meeting minutes, reports, service bulletins, publications and photographs which tell the story of the church. The records are divided into five main series, Background information; Vestry Records, Register of church services; Registers of baptisms, burials, marriages, communicants; Church Organizations, Church Activities, Printed Materials and Photographs.
Subjects:
Church records.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Detroit.; St. Andrew's Memorial Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Churches.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; St. Andrew's Memorial Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Background Information
  The Background series provides historical information about the church and also includes information on the memorials found in the church.
  - Boundary Investigation 1976 (Box 1)
  - Church History, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Memorials (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings & articles (Box 1)
  - St. Andrew's Case Study by Ken Lubega 1987 (Box 1)
  - Sale of Property (Box 1)
- Vestry Records
  The Vestry Records (1904-1988, 1 linear foot) series contains meeting minutes, treasurers reports, annual reports and correspondence all relating to the running of the church. These items are arranged into subseries in alphabetical order. Also included in this series are a few baptismal and communion records.
  - Correspondence
    - 1912, 1915, 1920 (Box 1)
    - 1936-1941, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1949-1955, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1957 (Box 1)
    - 1964-1975, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1980s (Box 1)
  - Meeting Minutes
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1909-1918, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1936, 1937 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1954, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1975, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Annual Parish Meeting Minutes 1977, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Membership 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - Parishoner Files
    - Baptismal Certificates (Box 1)
    - Bequest Letters 1974, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Communicants 1957 (Box 1)
    - Evidence of Death (Box 1)
    - Membership List 1942 (Box 1)
    - Membership Survey 1965 (Box 1)
  - Pledge Committee (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Annual Reports 1954-1955, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - Mission Treasurer's Report 1915-1918 (Box 1)
    - Parochial Reports
      - 1954-1972, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - 1974-1985 (Box 1)
    - Rector's Annual Report
      - 1925, 1927-1928 (Box 1)
      - 1938-1939 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's Report 1914-1986 (scattered), 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Resolution re: Darlene Watkins 1975 (Box 1)
  - Self Study Committee 1961 (Box 1)
  - Vestry Letters 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - Vestry Officers List 1940-1964 (Box 1)
- Registers of church services 1889-1988
  The Registers of church services series is comprised of seven volumes dating from 1889 to 1988 with some gaps.
  - 1889-1902, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - 1904-1917, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - 1928-1988, 5 volumes (Box 2)
- Registers of baptisms, burials, marriages, communicants 1886-1988
  The Registers of baptisms, burials, marriages, communicants series is comprised of five volumes (includes three oversize volumes) and dates from 1886 to 1998.
  - 1886-1889 (Box 3)
  - 1902-1936 (Volume 1)
  - 1938-1958 (Volume 2)
    (includes baptisms, 1938-1954; communicants, 1938-1957; burials, 1937-1955; and marriages, 1938-1958)
  - 1954-1988 (Volume 3)
  - Register of marriages 1921-1938 (Box 3)
- Church Organizations
  The Church Organizations (1917-1984, .5 linear feet) series contains the records of the Church Service League and the Episcopal Church women. These records are mostly meeting minutes and treasurers reports, but provide good information on the humanitarian activities of the church.
  - Altar Guild & Acolytes 1977-1984 (Box 3)
  - Church Service League
    - Constitution 1922 (Box 3)
    - Meeting Minutes 1944-1952, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Membership List 1952 (Box 3)
    - Reports
      - 1947-1950 (Box 3)
      - Church Periodical Club 1948-1952 (Box 3)
      - President's Annual Report 1946-1947, 1956 (Box 3)
      - Secretary's Annual Report 1943-1947, 1949-1954 (Box 3)
      - Treasurer's Report 1944, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Episcopal Church Women
    - Annual Reports 1966-1968, 1976, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Meeting Minutes 1966-1969, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Financial Reports 1917-1918 (Box 3)
- Church Activities 1880s-1983
  Church Activities (1880s-1983, .3 linear feet) is a small series containing records relating to entertainment programs, the Sundays at St. Andrew's concert series and Camp Okema. Records types include programs, correspondence, newspaper clippings and financial records.
  - Camp Okema 1950
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Expenses (Box 3)
    - Program & Activities (Box 3)
  - Special Programs
    - 1880s-1920s (varied dates) (Box 3)
    - Sunday's at St. Andrew's 1983 (Box 3)
      includes newspaper clippings
- Printed Materials 1886-1986
  The Printed Materials (1886-1986, .5 linear feet) series contains weekly service bulletins, and two monthly publications, The Antiphon and the St. Andrew's Record. Of special interest in this series is the one issue of The Phoenix, the newsletter sent out after the fire in 1906 which depicts the extent of the damage done and was meant as a means of drumming up support to rebuild. Also included are service bulletins from special dedication services.
  - Church Service Bulletins 1886-1986
    - Special Services 1886-1935, 1944, 1960, 1965 (Box 3)
    - Weekly
      - 1951-1953, 2 volumes (Box 3)
      - 1954, 1960, 1962, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Window Dedications (Box 3)
  - Newsletters 1908, 1914 (Box 3)
  - St. Andrew's Record, 1904-1908 (Box 3)
  - The Antiphon
    - 1938-1944, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1948-1953, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 3)
  - The Phoenix, November 17, 1906 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs (.4 linear feet) contains many images of the church building, both interior and exterior. There are also photos of the Episcopal Bishops of Michigan as well as some of the clergy of St. Andrew's. This series is arranged alphabetically by topic of the photographs.
  - Bishops of Michigan (Box 3)
  - Church Exterior (Box 3)
  - Church Fire 1906 (Box 3)
  - Church Interior (Box 3)
  - Clergy (Box 3)
  - General (Box 3)
  - St. Andrew's Choir 1912 (Box 3)
  - Stirton Dinner 1956 (Box 3)